Greeting Earthlings.
If you follow the channel, you know that we
are hard at work restoring the Apollo communication
hardware.
It all started simply enough, with just the
spacecraft S-Band transponder and the traveling
wave amplifier, that we picked up from collector
Steve Jurvetson.
But it got progressively more complete, as
we found and added more pieces to this complex
system, both on the spacecraft side and on
the ground side, thanks more pieces from Steve,
Marcel and other generous collectors.
It’s getting so involved, that we had to
add a replica of the control panel to manage
it all.
But we are far from done.
The system is so complex, that we still have
quite a few more boxes to restore and add.
For one, we have been powering it up with
a modern 400 Hz 3-phase AC power supply.
Now, wouldn’t it be nice, if we used the
real spacecraft power supply inverter instead.
[Marc]: Mike and Eric...
[Eric] Hello!
[Marc] ...what is this big chunk of metal
you're working on?
[Eric] It's very heavy!
[Mike] This is a Block I inverter.
So, one of three of these, that were installed
in the Command Module, that took in 28 volts
DC and put out 115 Volt RMS three-phase 400
Hertz AC power.
[Marc] The good avionics AC.
So one kilowatt, 1.5 kilowatt-ish each, right?
One for each fuel cell, which was 1.3 kilowatt,
something like that.
To better understand the role of the inverters,
we need to look at the Apollo Command and
Service Module power system for a moment.
The heart of it consists of 3 fuel cells,
which make electricity by reacting oxygen
and hydrogen, stored in liquid cryogenic form.
This produces both electricity and drinkable
water.
We explained the fuel cells and their failure
on Apollo 13 in a previous episode, which
I’ll link in the doodly-doo.
But I’ll recap quickly here.
The fuel cells were quite powerful, at a max
rating of 1.42 kWatts each.
They produced the power for the whole spacecraft,
in the form of DC voltage, varying from 27V
to 31V, depending on how hard you ran them.
They had three fuel cells, but the whole mission
could run on only two, and, as NASA diminutively
puts it in their operations handbook, you
could successfully terminate a mission on
just one.
Of course, on Apollo 13, they lost all three,
and they were lucky to have the LM attached,
or the situation would not have been recoverable.
The fuel cell power was distributed over thick
conductors called busses, Main DC Bus A and
Main DC Bus B. Normally, Fuel Cell 1 powers
Main Bus A, Fuel Cell 3 powers Main Bus B,
and Fuel Cell 2 is connected to either A,
B or both, as a backup.
And that’s why you hear the famous Main
B Bus undervolt call on Apollo 13.
[Apollo 13 Audio]
LOVELL: Hey Houston, we've had a problem
CAPCOM: OK
HOUSTON: Standby, they've got a problem
LOVELL: We have a Main B Bus undervolt
They had just lost Fuel Cell 1 and 3.
At the Apollo 13 accident time, the backup
Fuel Cell 2 was connected to Bus A, so only
the Bus B voltage went to zero, hence the
Main Bus B Undervolt caution light.
However, you can manually switch any fuel
cell to any bus, and you hear them at first
try to reconnect fuel cells to the default
configuration, cell 1 on bus A, and cell 3
on bus B.
EECOM: Flight Eecom
FLIGHT: Go ahead
EECOM: He's got fuel cells 1 and 3 are offline.
We got main A volts, we have no main B volts.
Have him attempt to reconnect the fuel cells.
Fuel cell 1 to Main A, fuel cell 3 to Main
B. Just try that.
CAPCOM: 13 Houston, we'd like you to attempt
to reconnect fuel cell 1 to Main A, and fuel
cell 3 to Main B.
This will of course fail, as both fuel cells
are already gone, and the remaining fuel cell
2 will be nursed to last an agonizing 90 more
minutes before being shut down
HAISE: OK, Houston, I'm showing...
I tried to reset and fuel cell 1 and 3 are
both showing grey flags, but they are both
showing zip on the flows.
EECOM: I copy Flight
CAPCOM: We copy
EECOM: Let me commiserate on that
Note that on this drawing from Apollo 17,
Fuel Cell 2 has a big 400 amp/hour battery
backup.
Couldn’t they just switch that on?
Well, you bet they did not have that one on
Apollo 13.
It was added on 14 after the accident.
Hindsight is always 20/20, as they say.
Note that on this drawing from Apollo 17,
Fuel Cell 2 has a big 400 amp hour battery
backup.
Couldn’t they just switch that on?
Well, you bet they did not have that one on
Apollo 13.
It was added on 14 after the accident.
Hindsight is always 20/20, as they say.
But enough for the DC power.
What we want to discuss AC power.
The spacecraft had two AC busses, powered
by 3 inverters, one of which we are about
to open.
The inverters converted the DC power from
the fuel cells to AC power, namely 115 Volts,
400 Hz, 3 phase AC, which had been the standard
for aircraft AC for over half a century.
The inverters were quite beefy, rated at 1.25
kWatts each.
Since we have 3 fuel cells and 3 inverters,
you’d think one inverter would be assigned
to each fuel cell, but the system is more
flexible than that.
As you can see here, inverter 1 is powered
by Main Bus A, Inverter 2 by Main Bus B, and
Inverter 3 by either Main A or Main B.
Each inverter AC output can be connected to
two busses, AC 1 or AC 2.
In the normal config , Inverter 1 powers AC
1, Inverter 2 powers AC 2, and Inverter 3
is on standby, connected to nothing.
Note that unlike the fuel cells, which you
could pile up on the same DC bus, you cannot
connect two inverters at the same time to
the same AC bus, because of phase issues.
However, there was flexibility to connect
any inverter to any AC bus if needed.
A complicated set of motorized relays implemented
automatic interlocks, preventing to connect
more than one inverter at a time to the same
AC bus.
So, you should now be able understand why
they lost AC 2 on Apollo 13.
Main DC Bus B went down, and that’s the
one that powers inverter 2.
So inverter 2 went down, and that took out
AC Bus 2, taking with it the telemetry sensors
that were connected to it.
Sensors that will become quite important pretty
soon.
You can hear them realizing that, early in
the debug.
EECOM: It does appear we've lost AC Bus 2
voltage.
Main B is reading 4 Volts, and that effectively
takes AC 2 away from us.
By the way, that was the voice of our engineering
hero Sy Liebergot, manning the EECOM console
at the time of the accident.
EECOM stands for Electrical, environmental
and consumables.
The EECOM will get quite a workout during
Apollo 13, and get everything just about right
in a very confusing situation.
About 10 minutes after the accident, way before
it will all get confirmed, EECOM reluctantly
comes to the conclusion that they have lost
a large amount of pressure in oxygen tank
1, lost fuel cell 1 and 3, and that they blew
a sphere, which is one of their pressurized
tanks.
EPS: We might have a pressure problem in the
fuel cell, it looks like
EECOM: Yeah
EPS: Seemed to happen simultaneously
EECOM: That can't be!
EPS: I can't believe that right off the bat,
but they are not feeding current
EECOM: Yeah, if you believe that N2 pressure
we blew a sphere!
EPS: Yeah, we might have lost fuel cell 1,
and it looks like fuel cell 3 is gone too!
The other voice you just heard is from our
behind the scene hero number two, Dick Brown,
manning the EPS, the Electricity Power System
officer, in the back room.
Sy will heavily rely on Dick for the whole
debug.
In the meantime, Sy passes on the bad news
to ECS, the Environmental Control Systems
engineer.
EECOM: And ECS Eecom
ECS: Go ahead
EECOM: Larry, I am almost afraid to think
that we lost our O2 tank 1,
or we busted the manifold or something.
Why, that pressure shouldn't be down that
far.
So, right now, the only remaining source of
power is fuel cell number 2, powered by the
dwindling pressure in Oxygen Tank 1.
About 16 minutes in, EPS asks for an immediate
reduction of the power consumption, once again
the correct move.
EPS: Eecom this is EPS
EECOM: Go
EPS: I think we ought to start powering down
EECOM: Yeah
EPS: Can we...
let's keep the power down
FLIGHT: Eecom do you want to go through that again, what do you want to power down to?
EECOM: I want to power down a total of 10A,
Flight
FLIGHT: A total of 10A!?
EECOM: That's affirm
FLIGHT: Okay
After that first emergency power down, which
takes a while to figure out, we are about
25 minutes in.
Sy shifts his focus to confirming the status
of Oxygen Tank 2.
O2 Tank 2 would be their only hope to power
Fuel Cell 2, if tank 1 keeps leaking out.
But remember our off-line inverter 3 and our
dead AC Bus 2?
Well, Sy has not been able read the O2 Tank
2 pressure since the accident, because the
pressure sensor is powered by the now dead
AC Bus 2.
He then asks Gene Kranz to prioritize the
re-powering of AC bus 2, so he can check on
O2 Tank 2.
EECOM: Hey EPS Eecom
EPS: Go
EECOM: We gotta get inverter... we gotta get
AC2 back temporarily so we can see what's
going on with the O2 pressures!
O2 Tank 2 pressure.
EECOM: Flight Eecom
FLIGHT: Go Eecom
EECOM: Okay I need one thing right now.
He's powering down, he's down to 41 amps total
spacecraft.
I'd like to get my AC 2 bus back, so I can
look at O2 Tank 2 pressure.
I have had no insight into that.
FLIGHT: Okay.
EECOM: Let's get, uh, I guess we can put the
inverter 3 to Main A - AC2
Inverter 3 is indeed the only other inverter
that be configured to be powered by Main A,
and can be connected to the AC 2 bus.
But this will not get done, because Gene pushes
back.
He is still in power reduction mode, and worried
about creating additional problems.
EECOM: Let's just do it temporarily
FLIGHT: Let me ask you a question.
Before you do that, would you like to make
sure you got all AC loads you don't need isolated
from the bus?
EECOM: No, let's not do that right now Flight.
I think we're in good shape that way, main
A is up high enough where it can handle the
inverter
FLIGHT: A thing that concerns me, is throwing
equipment - we had a problem, we don't know
the cause of the problem
That’s when Sy, who had suspected that Fuel
Cell 1 and 3 were gone from the very first
minutes after the accident, finally breaks
the bad news to Gene Kranz for the first time.
It’s about 20 minutes in.
EECOM: Flight I've got a feeling we've lost
two fuel cells.
I hate to put it that way but...
I don't know why we've lost them.
It doesn't all tag up.
And it's not an instrumentation problem, to
the best I can tell right now.
FLIGHT: Okay, I'll tell you what, let's discuss
this for just a little bit longer there, Sy.
Capcom start moving them back towards the
PTC attitude.
Gene is still reluctant.
You have to realize that he is on the flight
loop.
He has heard nothing of the backroom conversations
between EECOM and EPS like we have done here,
on this after the fact composite loop.
All he’s heard so far, were the various
recommendations by EECOM to switch things
around while reducing power draw.
Then Dick Brown has a brainwave.
He realizes that, although you cannot put
two inverters on one AC bus, you *can* put
one inverter on two AC busses.
Inverter 1 is working fine right now, powered
from the still good Main A. That will also
save the power draw of bringing up another
inverter.
EPS: Hey Sy? EECOM: Go ahead
EPS: Why don't you put one inverter on both busses
It will save about 4A.
We can try AC inverter 1 on both AC busses.
EECOM: You want inverter 1 on both AC busses?
EPS: Right
EECOM: Okay
EECOM: Flight Eecom
FLIGHT: Go Eecom
EECOM: I got a little correction.
Let's put inverter 1 on both AC busses, please
FLIGHT: Inverter 1 on both AC?
EECOM: That's affirm.
Gene is still nervous about the move and asks
a second time.
FLIGHT: OK, so, you want to configure inverter
1 on both AC busses?
EECOM: That's affirm, Flight
You can tell he's still worried about making
a blunder.
He asks a third time for himself, then fully
commits to it and gives the go-ahead.
What they are about to discover is startling.
FLIGHT: You want to put inverter one in both
AC busses?
Eecom and Capcom let's do it.
CAPCOM: Okay.
CAPCOM: 13 Houston, we need to get some more
instrumentation up.
We'd like you to put inverter 1 on both AC
buses, over.
FLIGHT: Eecom Flight
EECOM: Flight Eecom
FLIGHT: Monitor this bird when we switch it
in
EECOM: Will do
SWIGERT: Okay
This segment it hard to hear, but behind the
chatter, you can hear the answer from the
pressure reading.
ECS: Hey Bill O2 Tank 2 pressure.
OK, it's low, it's been low.
It looks like the culprit is probably venting.
In fact, it's probably the one that blew up
if anything it caused... it caused the problem.
EPS: Okay I see 19 PSI
ECS: Right
It’s 19 PSI.
It should be 900, not 19.
The second oxygen tank that they were counting
on is no more.
That’s the one that caused the problem in
the first place.
Gene is eager to find out, if his caving in
for the request was worth it.
And Sy is so taken aback by the reading, that
he asks for some time to take it all in.
FLIGHT: Okay, you got two good AC busses.
What did all that tell you now?
EECOM: It... it tells me... that, uh... well...
just give me about two more minutes, Flight
FLIGHT: Okay, take your time
Sy thinks the tank 2 is simply empty.
One way to confirm it is by looking at the
temperature.
EECOM: Trying to figure out what happened
to that O2 tank 2.
EPS: Right.
Now our pressure still should be good.
And you see, we got a low point...
EECOM: Why did the temperature drop so suddenly?
EPS: Because I probably don't have anything
left in it!
EECOM: Yeah!
And we're losing tank 1, if we can believe
it.
EPS: Uh, losing what?
EECOM: Tank 1 pressure!
EPS: Yeah!
EECOM: Do you think we blew the manifold?
EPS: It looks pretty good that we blew it
between the check valve and O2 tank 2!
Oh yes, they sure did blow the manifold, and
then much more.
They blew the whole tank.
Sy will never bother to answer Gene’s question.
He has already moved to the next step.
Tank 2 is a goner.
Instead, he immediately focuses on a few more
attempts to save what’s left on tank 1.
EPS asks that they try to turn on the heater
in tank 1, to see if the pressure will come
back up.
Tank 1 is now around 320 psi and dropping.
They need to beg for 5 Amps of power to turn
the heater on.
FLIGHT: Capcom, we want to get cryo O2 tank
number 1 heater on
CAPCOM: Roger, copy that, and we'd like to
build up the pressure in the O2 tank 1.
So turn the heaters on manually, we'll watch
the pressure for you
EECOM: Okay, 26.9V
FLIGHT: Did you see a 5A increase coming through Eecom?
EECOM: Do you see 5A increase here Dick?
EPS: That's affirm
EECOM: That's affirm, Flight
FLIGHT: Okay
EECOM: 26.7V, looks good.
We'll watch the pressure.
OK, this better works, or our Fuel Cell 3
will lose its oxygen supply.
How does the pressure look, Sy?
EECOM: ECS Eecom
EPS: Go!
EECOM: It looks grim!
EPS: Yes it does
EECOM: Get the 5A and no pressure increase
EPS: Just went down!
EECOM: It's going down, we're losing it!
EPS: Yes we are.
We are in serious problem if we can't get
any pressure, then we've got to power down
some more here
EECOM: That's right.
And luckily we've got the LM
EPS: Yeah but that's not gonna help this fuel cell
EECOM: That's right, we're gonna get it all
the way down
EPS: If we can't save that pressure, we're
gonna lose this third fuel cell
EECOM: Rog
Sy has realized it’s an abandon ship situation.
He tells flight to get the crew in the LM,
and admonishes his peer for the LM, called
the TELMU, to better get ready for an emergency
power up procedure.
EECOM: Flight Eecom
FLIGHT: Go ahead Eecom
EECOM: The pressure in O2 tank 1 is all the
way down at 297.
You better think about getting in the LM,
or using the LM systems.
TELMU: Go ahead Eecom
EECOM: Now let me tell you, we're in danger
of losing all three fuel cells.
So you guys get yourself geared up, okay?
TELMU: Rog we are working on right this minute...
EECOM: Get your power procedure now.
You guys had one worked out already, I think,
didn't you?
TELMU: That's right
EECOM: Okay
It’s about 40 minutes after the accident.
Sy has only one question for EPS now: how
long do we have to bring the LM up, before
running out of power in the command module?
EPS: Eecom?
EECOM: Go
EPS: Sy, looks like from the leak rate, that
we've got about 1 hour and 54 minutes left
until we are down to 100 PSI in tank 1.
Which is about the end of it for the fuel
cell
EECOM: Uh, Flight, we are gonna hit 100 PSI
in an hour 54 minutes.
That's the end, right there.
From there on, it’s a mad rush for an emergency
power up of the LM and a semi-graceful power
down of the CM.
But there will not be quite enough time before
Fuel Cell 2 conks out.
Which brings us to the subject of the battery
system.
So we are back in DC land, and there are a
few more busses we have not talked about yet,
in particular battery Bus A and battery Bus
B. On Apollo 13, which was lacking the big
service module battery backup added later,
these were powered by three small silver batteries,
at a measly 40 amp hour each.
These were only meant for powering the Command
Module during the short re-entry.
There a was provision to throw the batteries
on the Main DC busses, to cover for a usage
spike.
This was done by connecting, or tying, the
busses together, once again using a series
of motorized relays.
A few minutes into the accident, the ground
asks the astronauts to turn on the A/C bus
Tie, which will tie Battery Bus A with Main
A. Since only Battery A was on the Battery
Bus A, with backup Battery C on standby, this
action connected Battery A to Main A, to help
out the struggling fuel cell 2.
EECOM: Stand by, Flight.
Go EPS
EPS: Let's throw a battery on Bus B and Bus A
EECOM: Okay
EPS: Until we are sorted out.
We're getting undervolt.
EECOM: Flight, Eecom
FLIGHT: Go ahead Eecom
EECOM: Okay.
If we want to keep main...
SWIGERT: Houston, are you still reading 13?
EECOM: Stand by, he's finishing...
CAPCOM: Affirmative, we are reading you
EECOM: ...get battery A on Main A. Let's get
battery A on main A now
HAISE: OK Bus Tie A/C on
But as the situation gets worse, Houston needs
to save the re-entry batteries, and tells
the crew to take the tie off.
The astronauts immediately know why, realizing
full well the consequences of having used
part of their re-entry battery for the better
of 30 minutes.
EECOM: Flight, Eecom
FLIGHT: Go Eecom
EECOM: We really gotta get that battery off
the line and power down some more
FLIGHT: OK Sy, now how long to you want to
leave this battery online?
EECOM: I want to try to get it off as quick
as I can, but I need to get powered down.
EECOM: You want that battery off the line
now?
EPS: Yeah.
We can take it off now
EECOM: Okay.
Flight Eecom
FLIGHT: Go Eecom
EECOM: Let's take battery A off the main
FLIGHT: We can support the...
EECOM: That's right
FLIGHT: ...right now on the one fuel cell
even with the cry 2 going down?
EECOM: That's affirm, Flight
FLIGHT: OK.
What's your worry level on cry O2?
EECOM: Say again, Flight?
FLIGHT: OK, you want to...
EECOM: I want to save the battery, Flight
FLIGHT: Okay.
Pulling the battery A off, Capcom
CAPCOM: 13 Houston, turn the battery A off
SWIGERT: That's right, we were pulling current
all the time!
LOVELL: Battery A off, roger
However, an hour later, at the tail end of
the CM to LM transfer, Fuel Cell 2 is not
going to make it, and they desperately need
to keep the Command Module computer and the inertial
platform going, until they are able to transfer
inertial platform attitude angles to the LM.
They are now caught between a rock and hard
place.
Flight director Glynn Lunney decides, rightly,
to prioritize the transfer of the inertial
platform over saving the batteries.
They had just started to recharge battery
A. Glynn reverses that decision promptly.
FLIGHT: Capcom, Flight
CAPCOM: Go ahead
FLIGHT: When we get a little low, we are going
to have them pull batt A off (recharge), and
we get them put it on Main Bus A.
We are then going to hold up the IMU long
enough to get a coarse align in the LM.
And then we'll see whether we are going to
keep that coarse align or not.
But for right now we are running the profile,
then we'll have to determine it.
And keeping the coarse align they will, this
was a mission saving decision.
They will do a free return trajectory burn
a few hours later, and will not even have
to attempt a platform star alignment for the
precision abort burn at PC+2 after going around
the Moon.
After that, they’ll finally turn the LM
inertial platform and the computer off, to
save LM power.
Now, they are still not out of the woods in
terms of power.
They need to recharge their reentry battery
A that had saved them earlier.
They will do it, thanks to a cable meant to
recharge the LM batteries from the CM, and
a hacked procedure to use it in reverse, involving
100’s of circuit breakers.
[John Aaron, EECOM] There was a normal process
when you go into the moon, and coasting to
the Moon, that the command module supplied
a little electrical power to the lunar module.
What you could do through a precarious route,
is figure out some way to have that power
transfer come backwards.
Somehow we could arrange the circuitry, such
that the only thing that you would be powering
inside the Command Module, out of all the
hundreds and thousands of switches and circuit
breakers, was just this little thing called
a battery charger.
And we sent the crew over this checklist,
and they couldn't believe that we had devised
this little multi-page checklist, with hundreds
of circuit breakers and switches and all that
on it, to actually get to the battery charger.
But it worked!
[Marc] Alright, you are now Apollo spacecraft
power system experts, and should be able to
follow the raw Apollo 13 accident audio, which
is the best 2-1/2 hour customer service support
call you’ll ever hear.
I’ll link it in the doodly-doo.
But let’s get back to opening our inverter,
which was supposed to be the focus of the
video.
I know, we got sidetracked a bit…
[Marc] And this one, you identified?
[Mike] Yeah, it has written on the side here:
"B/P 14 use only".
B/P 14, boilerplate 14, was the North American
house spacecraft.
So this was the spacecraft that they had in
their Downey plant, that they did essentially
all their integration testing on.
Block 2 is very similar from the specification
control drawings we got.
It looks like they may have combined all of
these studs into circular connectors for Block 2.
You can see, it was laying on the floor of
the capsule, it has the angle.
So, laying upside down.
The three inverters were wedged under the
communications equipment, and had to conform
to the curved edge of the heat shield, laying
upside down.
And somebody apparently had that in his aircraft
or something.
And they had put goop on it, and there were
some stuff that is not original.
We cleaned it up.
So it sat on a hot plate - on a hot plate
- on a cold plate over here!
Which has a leak in it, it has a patch on
the other side.
And there is this really heavy copperish material,
that's supposed to be in between the two.
But somebody had added some goop on it, which
shouldn't be, of course, in a spaceship.
So we removed it as best as we could.
So, this one has seen some amateur use.
But it's a cool thing to have in your aircraft!
Yeah, we don't know what's in there.
There was a screw missing, there's some stuff
that doesn't belong.
So we're going to look at this stuff in there.
Right away there was something cheesy with
that unit.
Screws were missing, nuts were heard falling
inside, and we spied some strange looking
material.
So we took the Depstek endoscope, and got
greeted by strange stuff that did not look
quite right.
[Marc] A mouse!
[Eric] Almost looks like it, but it's not.
[Marc] So it doesn't look pretty inside.
I'm not sure if it's asbestos-y.
Why would you put that in there?
From then on, our voices will be a bit muffled,
because we all put on N95 masks.
And it turned out to be a good decision.
The screws or whatever was welded at the bottom,
just..
some of them went loose.
So this has had a tough life.
That's the weirdest piece of Apollo equipment
we ever opened up.
It's filled with this crap.
That would be an insulator.
It's very very light.
Yeah, I think you're right, it's - how do
you call it?
[Eric] Vermiculite.
[Mike] Yeah.
[Marc] Oh no, someone filled the thing with
vermiculite.
This was a test unit, so it was not potted,
and therefore you were not supposed to fly
it.
So probably the person that used it in his
airplane thought it would be a brilliant idea
to pot it with vermiculite.
Which is very light and insulating.
In fact, being an incredibly good thermal
insulator, it is just about the last thing
you’d want to fill a power supply with.
And to top it off, it’s extremely toxic.
Vermiculite is laced with the most deadly
form of asbestos.
Good thing we put our N95 masks on, but we
might still have gotten some of it.
Okay, so we're back at the inverter, the deadly
asbestos contaminated inverter.
Should be fairly clean, but we masked up just
in case.
Well, should be fairly clean, I'm sure there's
tons of particles coming out of it still.
It's a little sketch.
So you see, this is the 28 volt input, and
it's yay far from the from the heatsink or
the holder of that cap over here.
This is very tight.
There's another point you can see over here
that is super tight.
I saw another one that...
Yeah, I bent that one up, because it was so
close, I put it up.
So it's a little sketch, you have three of
the same thing here.
These guys are actually not transistors, they
are diodes.
They only have two connections to it, this
one is left floating, and this is true for
a lot of them, so that's on purpose.
We will have a lot of capacitors to check.
Plenty plenty plenty plenty plenty.
100 micro.
Lots of caps on this side.
Oh that's an SCR.
That is the main inverter.
Lots of transformers of course.
There's a huge one in the middle.
Underneath here, I think, that's a big transformer.
Some more out here.
A bit of a scary monster, that is.
We cleaned it off the best we could, but this
unit is just too contaminated for us to work
on it.
To make things worse, there were obvious signs
of corrosion.
We don’t have the schematics, but we have
a good block diagram and a short description
of how it works.
It’s all solid state, they use thyristors,
or SCRs, a buck converter, and magnetic amplifiers.
The final upvoltage conversion is done by
rotating magnetic fields in a specially wound
transformer to create an efficient power unit,
although very heavy due all the magnetics.
We went as far as testing a few capacitors.
We can’t really work on repairing this unit,
since it’s too contaminated.
One bad capacitor, and that would be the end
of it.
[Marc] Testing the caps in circuit, I guess,
will be the only thing we can do.
[Mike] Yeah.
[Marc] I bent it up because this was like
a fraction of a millimeter.
[Mike] Man, Block 1!
[Marc] So, my idea was just, check a few caps.
3.8 microfarad!
That starts good.
3.8, okay.
12 microfarad, so that looks okay.
100 microfarads, 92 microfarads, well that's
pretty good I would say.
550 microfarad!
What's up?
Some with too much capacitance?
Should we complain about it?
47, well they're all reasonably capacitive.
[Mike] hmm-hm.
[Marc] 34, 36, and 35.
So man, looks reasonable to me.
Okay, so the ones that are spot checkable,
check okay.
Over here, some over there.
It's full of caps basically.
[Mike] Yes.
[Marc] 2.5 microfarads on the dot.
[Mike] Yeah, 60 MFD.
[Marc] This big fellow reads 2.5 micro, but
it's written 68 on it. Hmm.
So I got the end out of it, so we can test
it out of circuit.
6 - no, 65 nanofarads.
Oh that's bad.
This one looks like it's a capacitor no more.
Yeah, so, the 1.8 microfarad is from the connection
it's attached to, and this one is not a capacitor anymore.
Okay, so, we have one bad one.
Which probably tells us, we just give up.
[Mike] Yep.
[Marc] 659 nanofarad.
So we have one example of one that died, which
is one too many, right?
They are so many capacitors all over the place.
[Mike] Yeah.
[Marc] We pack it all back together.
[Mike] Return to sender!
[Marc] We send it back.
Oh dang, I would have wanted to give it a
try, but it's not in working order.
[Mike] I'd be really curious to see what a
Block 2 inverter looks like on the inside,
considering they didn't change the part number.
They changed the dash number, but not the
part number.
[Marc] I'm being nice to the next owner of
this.
I'm making sure I put some tape.
It's cloth tape.
It's period correct, from teletype, it's just
the wrong color.
And places where there was stuff that could
be come in contact with the top cover.
And our dodgy one behind the 28 volt input.
So if somebody tries to fire it up, at least
you won't have these short circuits.
So it's all buttoned up, and Eric, who did
the bottom part of the cold plate, is reassembling it.
But that's it, bye bye inverter, I don't think
we'll power it up.
So we sealed it up in plastic bags and will
not touch it again, and had to take few days
off to wash every surface in the lab.
At least it taught us a bit about the command
module power system, and the incredible adventure
of Apollo 13.
So, don’t use collectible Apollo inverters
in your aircrafts, unless you have a team
of crack ground controllers to get your back,
and see you in the next episode!